Finding aid for the Xavier University Football Collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Football Collection
1901-1994
1919-1974
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
8.75 linear feet (16 boxes, including 5 boxes of scrapbooks)
This is a small collection containing photographs, correspondence, articles, programs, financial reports and attendance reports pertaining to the intercollegiate football team from Xavier University. This collection documents the highlights of the intercollegiate football team which existed through 1973 as well as several investigations into the feasibility of reviving an intercollegiate football team during the 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s.
XUA-82
History of Intercollegiate Football at Xavier University
Summary: Xavier University, then St. Xavier College, first established an intercollegiate football team in 1901. In 1922, Corcoran Field, a football stadium, was dedicated. The program continued, with the exception of 1943-1946, through the 1973 football season with one notable highlight being a 1950 Salad Bowl victory. After the 1973 season, the intercollegiate football team at Xavier was discontinued after several seasons of financial difficulties. Multiple attempts were made in the 1970s, 1980s and 1990s to revisit this issue and revive an intercollegiate football team at Xavier, but with no success.
Detail: Xavier University, then St. Xavier College, first established an intercollegiate football team in 1901. In 1922, Corcoran Field, a $40,000 football stadium, was dedicated to support the increasingly popular intercollegiate football team. Coach Joseph A. Meyer (tenure 1920-1935) played a notable role in the team's success. Starting in 1935, the football team experienced somewhat of a decline which was further exacerbated by World War II and the regulations which limited participation in intercollegiate athletics. From 1943-1946, there were no intercollegiate athletics including football due to difficulties related World War II. However, intercollegiate football returned to Xavier in 1946, and was thriving by 1949. In 1950, Xavier's football team won the Salad Bowl. However, by 1961, the Board of Trustees was already starting to question the expense associated with the football team. By 1971, the Board of Trustees noted significant financial losses associated with the football team and a significant decline in support for the football team. After the 1973 football season, it was determined that the intercollegiate football team at Xavier should be discontinued because it was no longer financially viable. Several attempts were made in the 1970s, 1980s and 1990s to revisit this issue and revive an intercollegiate football team at Xavier, but with no success. Corcoran Stadium was demolished in 1988.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the highlights of the intercollegiate football team at Xavier as well as several attempts to revive an intercollegiate football team after it was discontinued in 1973. The collection includes various publications, programs, photographs, correspondence, press releases, studies of the financial viability of the football program, and reports. Seven scrapbooks are also included.
Statement of Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series I: Media Guides and Press books
Series II: Programs
Series III: General correspondence, Events, Rosters, Newspaper Articles
Series IV: Discontinuation & Post-Discontinuation
Series V: Scrapbooks
Separated Material
5 boxes of scrapbooks (7 scrapbooks total) are shelved separately with oversized materials.
Restrictions on Access
There are no restrictions on access.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Football; College Sports--Ohio--History
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Series I: Media Guides and Press Books, 1938-1938, 1953-1973
  This series contains media guides, press books, etc. that were created by Xavier University to publicize the intercollegiate football team at Xavier. Materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Media Guides, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Media Guides, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Media Guides, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Media Guides, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Media Guides, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Football Programs, 1911, 1925-42. 1948-1973
  This series contains programs from Xavier's intercollegiate football games arranged chronologically. These programs include several programs produced by other schools and military organizations for games in which Xavier University participated. Please note that there was no intercollegiate football program at Xavier University from Fall 1943 to 1945.
  - Game Programs, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Game Programs, 1926 October-November (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Game Programs, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Game Programs, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Game Programs, 1929-1931 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Game Programs, 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Game Programs, 1934 September-November (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Game Programs (Duplicates), 1934 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Game Programs, 1935-1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Game Programs, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Game Programs, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Game Programs, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Game Programs, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Game Programs, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Game Programs, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Game Programs, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Game Programs, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series III: Football General Information, Correspondence, Events, Rosters, Newspaper Articles, 1901-1973
  This series contains general information pertaining to the intercollegiate football program at Xavier University from 1901 to 1973 when it was discontinued. This series includes many different types of documents and artifacts including newspaper articles and clippings, correspondence, memoranda, team rosters, and telegrams. Financial information pertaining to the program is contained as well. A limited number of photographs are also included in this collection.
  - 1901 Team Picture - Newspaper clipping (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Oh Those Mighty Jesuits (St. X.) of 50 Years Ago.," Cincinnati Enquirer, 1969 October 12 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Copies of Newspaper articles, etc., 1919-1923 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Football Rosters & Records, 1919-1924, 1934-1937 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Game Ticket, St. Xavier v. Haskell Indians, (circa 1919-1929) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Xavier vs. Lees Game, 10/1927 (Newspaper article circa 1970's) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Ticket; Handwritten statistics, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Cincinnati Bengals Professional Programs, Xavier Alumni Players, 1934, circa 1937-1941 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Schedule, Coach & Team Background, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Football Publicity - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Joe Meyer Resigns Position As Xavier Football Coach," misc. clippings, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Football Publicity - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Football Publicity - Correspondence, Telegrams, etc., 1937 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Schedules, Ticket Info., 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Publicity - Football, Correspondence, etc., 1938 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Nebel All-Star Contest, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Crow, Clem, Head Football Coach (1935-1943) --Publicity Committee, Gift fund, 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous - Rosters, Schedule, etc., 1939 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Publicity - Football, Correspondence, Contracts, etc., 1939 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Football Schedule, etc., 1940 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - American Legion All-Star, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Sheetz-All-Star Contest, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Football - Publicity, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Sun Bowl Game, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper Articles, Publicity, Photos, Telegrams, etc., 1935-1943 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Football Newspaper Clippings, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous-Rosters, Schedules, Coach & Team Info. & Bio., 1947-1948 Seasons (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Varsity letter Awards, 1947-1949 (includes other sports) (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Newspaper Articles and Clippings, 1949 Season (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Governor's Trophy, Xavier vs. University of Dayton, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Newspaper articles, (St. Xavier High School?), circa 1900-1920?, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Salad Bowl Game, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, Press releases, 1950 Season (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Press Releases, Articles, etc., 1951 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - College Football: Asset or Liability, 1951; Steiner, Celestin J., S.J., (President of Xavier Univeristy) (Box 6, Folder 3a)
  - U.C. vs. Xavier, 11/17/1951 (Article, circa. 1977) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Legion of Honor, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, etc., 1952 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Kluska, Edward L. (Head Coach 1947-1954), 1952 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Press Releases, correspondence, Newspaper articles, etc., 1953 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Collegiate Record Book, Appointment of Harry Connoly (Head Coach), 1955 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, Articles, etc., 1956 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Press Releases, Statistics, etc., 1957 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Statistics, etc., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous - Roster, Statistics, etc., 1960, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Football brochures, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, etc., 1969 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Selcer, Richard J. (Head Football Coach, 1970-1971), includes photographs (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Football schedule, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Freshman Football, 1950, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Spring Football, 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Football Banquets - Programs, 1932-1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Football Banquets - Correspondence, etc., 1934-1948 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Football Banquet - Address by Very Rev. Paul O'Connor, S.J. (President of Xavier University), 1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Football Jamborees, 1938-1943 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Athletic Review Financial Info., Correspondence, etc., 1934-1936 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Athletic Review Financial Info., Correspondence, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Athletic Review Correspondence, Financial Info., 1938 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Athletic Review Correspondence, Financial Info., etc., 1939 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Reservations of Box Seats, 1925-1935 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Faculty and Employee Football Passes - Correspondence, 1934, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Football Financial Statements, 1935-1947 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Football Gross Income Summary, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1961 Football Financial Info., From Xavier University Athletic Board (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Discontinuation & Post-Discontinuation, 1973-1994
  This series contains information pertaining to the discontinuation of intercollegiate football at Xavier University and the attempts to revive an intercollegiate football team at Xavier. This series contains reports, correspondence, and financial projections pertaining to the achievability of bringing back an intercollegiate football team at Xavier University.
  - Report on Xavier University's Football Program, 1973 May 16; Cecchini, Tom (Head Football Coach) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence; A Report to the Board of Trustees: A Recommendation for the future of Intercollegiate Football at Xavier University (2 copies), circa 1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Football Program Discontinuation Newspaper Articles, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1975, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Silent Fall" [A History of Xavier Football], 1988-1989; Charles M. Hogan (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - In Support of Division III Football For Xavier University (To Begin Fall 1984), 1973-1984; Folder appears to be compiled by a unique person or group acting as part of a committee which was part of the Board of Trustees of the Musketeer Club. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - In Support of Division III Football For Xavier University (To Begin Fall 1984), 1968-1984; Appears to be a unique person or group part of the committee of the Board of Trustees of the Xavier Musketeer Club. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), Loose Accompanying Papers, Articles & Report, 1984, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), Membership List, Correspondence, etc. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), "Meeting I," 11/23/1993, 1993 November (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), "Meeting II", 1993 December 14 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), "Meeting III", 1994 January 4 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), "Meeting IV", 1994 January 20 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), [Meeting V], 1994 January 27 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), "Title IX" (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), "Historical", 1932-1984 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), "Financial Info." [Part I] (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), "Financial Info." [Part II] (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), [Commitment to Equity: Self-Study], Undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), [Correspondence] (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), [Correspondence II] (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), [Miscellaneous], 1993-1994, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Football Feasibility Task Force (1993-1994), [Correspondence--Summary], 1994, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Xavier University Division IAA Non-Scholarship Football Feasibility Task Force Report, February 8, 1994, 1994 February 8 (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Series V: Scrapbooks, 1923-1973; The McQuaide Scrapbooks (Box 3) were compiled by Mr. James P. McQuaide and donated by Mrs. James P. McQuaide. Others were compiled by unknown individuals or organizations.
  This collection contains 7 scrapbooks, chronologically arranged, documenting events and people in the history of the intercollegiate football team at Xavier University.
  - 1923-1926 Football Seasons (Box 12, Volume 1)
  - 1949 Salad Bowl Game, 1949 December - 1950 January (Box 13, Volume 1)
  - McQuaide Football Scrapbooks, Vol. 1, 1933-1940; Mr. James P. McQuaide (Box 14, Volume 1)
  - McQuaide Football Scrapbooks, Vol. 2, 1936 - 1939; Mr. James P. McQuaide (Box 14, Volume 2)
  - McQuaide Football Scrapbooks, Vol. 3, 1940 -1948; Mr. James P. McQuaide (Box 14, Volume 3)
  - 1965 Football Season (Box 15, Volume 1)
  - 1972-1973 Football Season (Box 16, Volume 1)
    This is an unbound collection of scrapbook pages from the final 1972- 1973 intercollegiate football season at Xavier University. Many of these articles and clippings are undated and the source publication is not labeled. However, they appear to be from the 1972-73 season and many appear to be from the Cincinnati Enquirer. The person or group responsible for compiling this scrapbook is unknown.